<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: betweenness | Zhou's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://yoyzhou.github.io/blog/categories/betweenness/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yoyzhou.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-02T01:05:30-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://yoyzhou.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[yoyzhou]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Kinda Betweenness Centrality Algorithm]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoyzhou.github.io/blog/2013/04/29/a-kinda-betweenness-centrality-algorithm/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-29T15:06:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoyzhou.github.io/blog/2013/04/29/a-kinda-betweenness-centrality-algorithm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post I’d like to demonstrate a algorithm per computing the betweenness centrality which I have introduced in the previous post, for more details of what is Betweenness Centrality, and its measurements, please refer to my post <a href="/blog/2013/04/28/studying-notes-a-set-of-measures-of-centrality-based-on-betweenness/">A Set of Measures of Centrality Based on Betweenness</a>. </p>

<h4 id="definitions-and-notations">Definitions and notations</h4>

<p>Before getting down to the algorithm, first we briefly go through the definitions and notations.</p>

<p><strong><em>Betweenness Centrality</em></strong> is “the degree to which a point falls on the shortest path between others”, it’s the core of the algorithm. Although computing <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shortest_path_problem">shortest path</a> between point pair is essential to our problem, shortest path algorithm will not be the focus of this post. Readers interested in shortest path algorithm please refer to the shortest path on Wikipedia page <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shortest_path_problem">here</a>, kindly note that even if you have no knowledge of shortest path algorithm, it will not affect you reading this post.</p>

<p>In the next section, we use graph-theoretic terminology neutral to interpretation of notations.</p>

<p>Given a <em>directed graph</em> <script type="math/tex">\begin{smallmatrix} G = \left( V, E \right) \end{smallmatrix}</script>, consists of a set of $V$ of vertices and a set of $E \subseteq V \times V$ of <em>derected</em> edges.</p>

<p>Denote $\sigma(s, t)$ to the number of <em>shortest</em> $(s, t)$-paths, some times called geodesics, and let <script type="math/tex">\sigma(s,t \vert v)</script> be the number of shortest path which passing through certain vertex $v$ other than $s, t$, then the <em>betweenness centrality</em> $C_B(v)$ of vertex $v \in V$ is defined to be:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">\begin{align}  C_B(v) = \sum\limits_{s,t \in V} \frac{\sigma(s,t \vert v)}{\sigma(s, t)} \end{align}</script>

<h4 id="the-algorithm">The Algorithm</h4>
<p>As quoted from “On variants of shortest-path betweenness centrality and their computation”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Efficient computation of betweenness is based on the fact that the cubic number of <em>pair-wise dependencies <script type="math/tex">\delta(s,t \vert v) = \sigma(s, t \vert v)/ \sigma(s, t)</script></em> can be aggregated without computing all of them explicitly.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Defining one-side dependencies:</p>

<p><script type="math/tex">\begin{align} \delta(s \vert v) = \sum\limits_{t \in V} \delta(s, t \vert v)\end{align}</script>,</p>

<p>per <script type="math/tex">\forall s, v \in V</script> we can exploit that</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">\begin{align} \delta(s \vert v) = \sum\limits_{w: (v, w) \in E  \ and \\\ dist(s, w) = dist(s, v) + 1} \left[ \frac{\sigma(s,v)}{\sigma(s, w)}
\times \left( 1 + \delta(s \vert w) \right) \right]
\end{align}</script>

<p>where $dist(s, t)$ denotes the minimum path length of point pair $(s, t)$.</p>

<p>The algorithm asserts that the dependency of a vertex $s$ on some $v$ can be compiled from dependencies on vertices <strong><em>one edge farther away</em></strong>. </p>

<p>Since $w$ is connected to $v$ and <strong>one edge farther away</strong> (which determined by <script type="math/tex">dist(s, w) = dist(s, v) + 1</script>) from $v$, so point $v$ is on the shortest paths of $(s, w)$ and the proportion of betweenness value that $v$ gains from edge $(v, w)$ equals to $\frac{\sigma(s,v)}{\sigma(s, w)} \times 1$; the other part of betweenness gain is from point $w$, that <script type="math/tex">\frac{\sigma(s,v)}{\sigma(s, w)} \times \delta(s \vert w)</script>, thus sum of the above two parts of betweenness gain is what exactly the equation demonstrates.</p>

<h4 id="references">References</h4>

<p>[1] Linton C. Freeman. A set of measures of centrality based on betweenness. Sociometry, 40(1):35–41, March 1977.</p>

<p>[2] Ulrik Brandes. On variants of shortest-path betweenness centrality and their generic computation. Social Networks, 30(2):136–145, May 2008.</p>

<p><code>---EOF---</code></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Set of Measures of Centrality Based on Betweenness]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoyzhou.github.io/blog/2013/04/28/studying-notes-a-set-of-measures-of-centrality-based-on-betweenness/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-28T23:49:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoyzhou.github.io/blog/2013/04/28/studying-notes-a-set-of-measures-of-centrality-based-on-betweenness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is a studying notes of paper “A Set of Measures of Centrality Based on Betweenness”, the paper <a href="https://www.tribler.org/trac/raw-attachment/wiki/ReputationFunction/23.pdf">[pdf]</a>, wrote by Freeman in 1977, is an introductory and the most classic paper of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Betweenness_centrality">betweenness centrality</a>. Based on the betweenness centrality concept first introduced by Bavelas in 1948, the paper introduces a set of measures of centrality, including point centrality, scale free (relative) point centrality, and graph centrality. </p>

<h4 id="betweenness-and-point-centrality">Betweenness and Point Centrality</h4>

<p>The classical centrality measures of Bavelas (1950) etc. can not be used by unconnected networks, since they define the centrality of a point as the sum of the minimum distance between that point and all others, thus all distance sums are infinite in unconnected networks.  </p>

<p>In order to obtain a more satisfactory solution per centrality measurements, Freeman adopts the betweenness concept first introduced by  Bavelas, betweenness of a point is “the degree to which a point falls on the shortest path between others”, and therefore has a potential per control of communication, persons in such central positions could influence the group by “ withholding information (or) coloring, or distorting it in transmission”.</p>

<h4 id="measurement-of-point-centrality">Measurement of Point Centrality</h4>
<p>Consider a unordered pair of  points {<script type="math/tex">p_i, p_j</script>} <script type="math/tex">(i \neq j)</script>. Either <script type="math/tex">p_i \text{ and } p_j</script> are unreachable from each other or  there are one or more paths between them. In the later case, each path has a length equals to the number of edges contained in it. Among the paths connecting pi and pj, one or more have the shortest length: the <strong>geodesics</strong>.</p>

<p>If $p_i$ and $p_j$ are unreachable from each other, then <script type="math/tex">b_{ij}(p_k)</script>, denotes betweenness centrality of point <script type="math/tex">p_k</script> with respect to <script type="math/tex">p_i</script> and <script type="math/tex">p_j</script>, is zero;</p>

<p>If <script type="math/tex">p_i</script> and <script type="math/tex">p_j</script> are <em>adjacent</em>, means that there is only one edge connecting them, since <script type="math/tex">p_k</script> does not reside on the shortest paths of <script type="math/tex">p_i</script> and <script type="math/tex">p_j</script>, <script type="math/tex">b_{ij}(p_k)</script> also equals to zero;</p>

<p>If <script type="math/tex">p_k</script> is on one or more shortest paths of <script type="math/tex">p_i</script> and <script type="math/tex">p_j</script>, in which situations, <script type="math/tex">p_k</script> has a proportional control of communication between <script type="math/tex">p_i</script> and <script type="math/tex">p_j</script>, and intuitively the proportion is the percentage/extent to which <script type="math/tex">p_k</script> is on the shortest paths, given the total shortest paths of <script type="math/tex">p_i</script> and <script type="math/tex">p_j</script> is <script type="math/tex">g_{ij}</script> and the number of <script type="math/tex">p_k</script> falls in the shortest paths is <script type="math/tex">g_{ij}(p_k)</script>, then we get <script type="math/tex">b_{ij}(p_k) = g_{ij}(p_k)/g_{ij}</script>. As the equation shows below:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[
b_{ij}(p_k) = \begin{cases} 
0 & p_i \mbox{ and } p_j \mbox{ are unreachable or adjacent} \\ 
g_{ij}(p_k)/g_{ij} & \text{otherwise} 
\end{cases} %]]&gt;</script>

<p>To determine the overall centrality of <script type="math/tex">p_k</script> in the graph, we need merely to sum the partial betweenness value of all unordered pair of points {<script type="math/tex">p_i, p_j</script>} in the graph:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">\begin{align} C_B(p_k) = \sum\limits_{i}^n \sum\limits_{j}^n b_{ij}(p_k) \mbox{ where } i \lt j \mbox{ and } i,j \neq k  \end{align}</script>

<h4 id="scale-free-point-centrality">Scale-free Point Centrality</h4>

<p>One problem with the above point centrality is it not point independent/scale-free, it is related to how many points in the graph, thus comparing point centrality defined above with different graphs which may contain different amount of point is meaningless. A concreted example is pointed out that  6 betweenness value in 5 points graph compared with 6 betweenness value in 25 points graph, although they have the same betweenness centrality value but the influence of them is different.</p>

<p>In the later section Freeman introduced a relative point centrality, which is scale free to how many points in the graph, where point centrality <script type="math/tex">C'_B(p_k)</script> is divided by the maximum centrality of their graph.</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">\begin{align} C'_B(p_k) = \dfrac{\sum\limits_{i}^n \sum\limits_{j}^n b_{ij}(p_k)} {\mbox{Max } C_B(p_k^*)} \end{align} </script>

<p>where <script type="math/tex">n</script> is the number of points in the graph, and <script type="math/tex">\begin{smallmatrix} \text{Max } C_B(p_k^*) \end{smallmatrix}</script> is only determined by n, which is <script type="math/tex">\begin{smallmatrix} \frac{n \times (n-1)}{2} - (n-1) = \frac{n^2 - 3n + 2}{2} \end{smallmatrix}</script>, therefore we obtain:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">\begin{align} C'_B(p_k) = \dfrac{2 \times \sum\limits_{i}^n \sum\limits_{j}^n b_{ij}(p_k)}{n^2 - 3n + 2} \end{align} </script>

<p>To get more information of how <script type="math/tex">\begin{smallmatrix} \text{Max } C_B(p_k^*) \end{smallmatrix}</script> is computed, please refer to the paper for details, you can imagine such a point that stands on the shortest path of all other pairs of {<script type="math/tex">p_i, p_j</script>}, where <script type="math/tex">p_i</script> and <script type="math/tex">p_j</script> have merely <strong>one</strong> shortest path, such a graph looks like a star graph, that one point in the central and all others surround it.</p>

<h4 id="graph-centrality">Graph Centrality</h4>

<p>Freeman defines the graph centrality as the average difference between the most central point and all others, which sounds like a little bit of <strong><em>information entropy</em></strong>, I think.</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">\begin{align}
C'_B = \dfrac{\sum\limits_{i}^n \left( C'_B(p_k^*) - C'_B(p_k) \right)}{n - 1} 
\end{align}</script>

<p>where <script type="math/tex">\begin{smallmatrix} C'_B(p_k^*) \end{smallmatrix}</script> is the relative point centrality value of the most central point <script type="math/tex">p_k^*</script> in the graph.</p>

<p>From the equation, we can see if all the points have the same centrality value then the graph centrality is 0; and if the graph is a star or wheel graph, then graph centrality is 1.</p>

<p><code>---EOF---</code></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
